<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: wtf | sharp bites]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/categories/wtf/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-03T21:30:34+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[alberto]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java and (the lack of) CoC]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2009/10/16/java-and-lack-of-coc/"/>
    <updated>2009-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2009/10/16/java-and-lack-of-coc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<blockquote>   <p>&quot;Java is a DSL to transform big Xml documents into long exception stack traces.&quot;</p>   <cite>- Scott Bellware</cite></blockquote>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What do you see on the picture?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2009/09/15/what-do-you-see-on-picture/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2009/09/15/what-do-you-see-on-picture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; float: left; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_kQ7iivKjVno/Sq9dG5dZPCI/AAAAAAAAAL8/Z4vqxop7-cY/s1600-h/monofinger.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_kQ7iivKjVno/Sq9dG5dZPCI/AAAAAAAAAL8/Z4vqxop7-cY/s320/monofinger.jpg" /></a></div><a href="http://monotouch.net/">Monotouch</a> 1.0 was released today. I was quite shocked when I saw the logo. Look at it for a second. What do you see there?<br />It might be my perturbated mind, but I was quite shocked when I felt it was "showing me the finger". It actually took me a minute (I said I was shocked) to realize it was not <i>that </i>finger. Still, maybe that logo deserves a revamp. Just making clear the first finger is a thumb will suffice.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why SVN sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2008/09/26/why-svn-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2008/09/26/why-svn-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;" trbidi="on"><blockquote>"A common desire is to refactor source code, especially in Java-based software projects. Files and directories are shuffled around and renamed, often causing great disruption to everyone working on the project. Sounds like a perfect case to use a branch, doesn't it? Just create a branch, shuffle things around, and then merge the branch back to the trunk, right?<br /><br />Alas, this scenario doesn't work so well right now and is considered one of Subversion's current weak spots."</blockquote><cite>- Subversion book</cite><br /><br />The fact that subversion lacks a true rename operation (it is done via copy &amp; delete) you can get into a lot of troubles if you rename or move files in subversion if somebody else modifies the same file meanwhile. And by troubles I mean losing data! (If you want more info about it, check <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=2282">this bug entry</a>. You will find the detailed use cases in the attached files there.)<br /><br />For a fast rename (or move, which is exactly the same operation) &amp; commit, there is a low probability you run into this issue (assuming the other guy also updates frequently), so things aren't so critical here. But, when working with branches, it's a whole new story. They will live much longer (from days to weeks or months) so the probability of somebody modifying a file renamed in another branch increases a lot. That effectively means you cannot rename or move files if you use branches. Yeah, you read it right. If you use branches, moving files <span style="font-weight: bold;">is not safe</span>. End of story.<br /><br />So, what svn is forcing us to do is either:<br />a) Don't rename files.<br />b) Don't use branches.<br />c) Don't use subversion.<br /><br />a) is simply stupid, so let's forget it. b) might be ok for some people/enviroments. c) is what you really should be doing if b) is not an option (which makes perfect sense).<br /><br />If you are looking for alternatives, use git or mercurial.</div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
