<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: agile | sharp bites]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/categories/agile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-23T09:56:10+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[alberto]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A week at BeCode. Day 1: Anarchy in the UK]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2013/04/22/a-week-at-becode-day-1-anarchy-in-the-uk/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-22T22:57:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2013/04/22/a-week-at-becode-day-1-anarchy-in-the-uk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><iframe width="640" height="510" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/pOe9PJrbo0s " frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>

<p>Today was my first day at BeCode. If you measure productivity by lines of count written, then my productivity today would be exactly 0. (Also, you are an idiot. Stop doing that.)</p>

<p>The door was open when I arrived to The Cave (more on that later). I came in and met <a href="twitter.com/xav1uzz">Xavi</a> and <a href="twitter.com/elmendalerenda">Mike</a>. <a href="https://twitter.com/semurat">Jorge</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/jjballano">Jesús</a> were remote, so I didn't get to talk to them. There was also a guy whose name I don't remember (sorry mate!) who is not really part of BeCode, but is working there with them. He designs his own line of T-shirts. I spent some time talking with Xavi and Mike about BeCode and what they do now. It surprised me a lot when they told me they have decided not to work for clients anymore. They told me they now prefer to do workshops, consulting and hacking, and they would like to develop a product.</p>

<p>The big WTF of the day came when Xavi kicked me in the head with the fact that Mac OS X is not case-sensititive (srsly, Apple?). He later added something about the worst thing in the world being a PHP programmer. He mentioned something after that, but I was still shocked, so you better ask him. :)</p>

<p>When I woke up, I talked with Mike about a project he wants to do for his town-hall, to give people the ability to give feedback. We discussed about his motivations, what would constitute the MVP and how some of the features made sense or not. Then <a href="https://twitter.com/luislitze">Luis</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/circun4">Sergio</a> came and we went to buy some food for lunch.</p>

<p>In the afternoon, Sergio, showed me the very starting bits of a 2D videogame he wants to do. Mike told me he is going to teach a javascript course and we decided I would do it beforehand along the week and give him feedback.</p>

<p>Then I decided to have a look to <a href="https://github.com/beCodeMyFriend/Cuore.js">Cuore.js</a> source code while I waited for Xavi to come back from the gym (I know, I know, me too. Maybe he wants to get into Gandia Shore or something). When he arrived he told me what he wants to work on for the next version (was that secret? I hope not) and explained me the high level architecture of Cuore and how ReST was full of crap and how SOA was vastly superior. He  probably still was high on testosterone and I didn't want to get kicked again, so I just nodded and no one got hurt. We moved on to the code and paired, having him as the driver. I was surprised becaused I expected him to go much faster than what he did. Instead he took plenty of time with the code. We talked a lot about what we were trying to achieve, there was no rush at all. I decided I will be working with Xavi on Cuore for the rest of the week, too.</p>

<p>A random girl came in (remember the door was open? It remained open for the rest of the day. It turns out it's a rule to be approachable to passing byers) asking if we(they) fixed bikes. They don't, but they told her she needed a new wheel and where to buy it, and they offered to teach her how to replace it. She came back after a while and Luis did it. She paid back with some pastries.</p>

<p>I spent some more time talking with Xavi about his view on our so-called industry, the need to teach programming to children and other phylosophical aspects of our not-science-nor-craft field.</p>

<p>Finally, Luis and "Mate" showed us a couple of videos they had been editing of Luis doing vandal cycling in Valencia and New York.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A week at BeCode. Day 0: Hey Ho! Let's go!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2013/04/21/a-week-at-becode-day-0-hey-ho-lets-go/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-21T23:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2013/04/21/a-week-at-becode-day-0-hey-ho-lets-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><iframe width="640" height="510" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/ElX7x_qNUYQ " frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>

<p>This is a post series about my desksurfing at BeCode.</p>

<p>We coined the term <a href="http://www.desk-surfing.org/">desksurfing</a>  at the <a href="http://agile-spain.org/">Agile Spain</a> Open Space Conference we held back in 2011 in Pamplona (my hometown!). It’s akin to what some fellows like <a href="http://coreyhaines.com/">Corey Haines</a> and other journeymen were already doing. You go visiting another company to spend some time sharing experiences, programming and learning from each other. Cross-pollination for your brain.</p>

<p>Today, I traveled to Valencia for a week of desksurfing at <a href="http://www.becodemyfriend.com/?lang=en_us">BeCode</a>. They describe themselves as a “punk incubator”, and you can certainly tell they are not very “enterprisey”!</p>

<ul>
<li><p>They are so underground they don’t put their office address (or the cave as they call it) on their web. I had to look for it to know where it is. Fuck! I just realized they don’t even tell what they are or do, except for a few sample projects!</p></li>
<li><p>When I mailed them telling I wanted to go there, <a href="https://twitter.com/XaV1uzz">Xavi</a>’s answer was (quite literally): “awesome, call me when you get here”. That. Was. It. Then, when I arrived he didn’t answer the phone (he later told me <a href="https://twitter.com/XaV1uzz/status/326042040225890305">he was having a paella</a>, wtf! :D).</p></li>
<li><p>They hold free workshops in their office as part of their “neighbourhood development plan”, with topics as disparate as how to fix your bike or teaching kids html or programming with <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu/">scratch</a>. I think anyone can give a workshop there, they just have to ask for the space.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>What am I going to do this week? I’m not sure yet, and I just don’t really care (well, I was curious, so after I insisted Xavi I got some more info and he proposed a couple of interesting options to work with them, we'll see).</p>

<p>Then, why did I decide to come? AFAIK they are raw, honest, transparent and strong in their beliefs. And that resonates with me. I came here to live that, to see how they do things, to breathe their culture (and to share mine if they are interested). To have fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Change]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2011/10/23/change/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2011/10/23/change</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;" trbidi="on"><blockquote>“You never change things by ﬁghting the existing reality. To change something, build a new model that makes the existing model obsolete.” <cite> R. Buckminster Fuller</cite></blockquote></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Becoming an Agile Manager: Transforming the Three Dysfunctions of Management]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2011/04/15/becoming-agile-manager-transforming/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2011/04/15/becoming-agile-manager-transforming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
A terrific talk by Diana Larsen on <a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Managing-Agile">how to overcome 3 dysfunctional management traps</a>:&nbsp;magical thinking, illusion of control and individual blame using Agile.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I've read: Peopleware]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sharpbites.com/2010/11/26/ive-read-peopleware/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sharpbites.com/2010/11/26/ive-read-peopleware</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
'Peopleware' is one of those classic books of our profession, a must-read. Unfortunately, it's not easy to grab a copy of it on the stores (it may have been discontinued, I'm not sure).&nbsp;After a failed attempt to borrow it from <a href="http://twitter.com/jmbeas">Jose Manuel Beas</a>,&nbsp;a few weeks ago, I finally got the chance to read it (thanks <a href="http://twitter.com/rubenbpv">Rubén</a>!).<br /><br />All I can say is, if you have the chance, read it! Just so you can have a glimpse at it, here are some notes I&nbsp;took from it. Most are direct quotes,&nbsp;although&nbsp;I reworded a few to&nbsp;synthesize.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Productivity</span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: small;">As long as workers are crowded into noisy, disruptive space, it's not worth improving anything but the workspace.</span></span><br />Experiments showed projects without deadlines had the best productivity.<br />Better performance can be explained entirely by more effective ways of handling people, modifying the workplace and corporate culture.<br />Developers main work is human communication to organize the user's expressions of needs into formal procedure.<br />People won't work better under a lot of pressure.<br />The manager's function is not to make people work, but to make it possible for people to work.<br />Best people outperform the worst by 10 and the median performer by 2.5.<br />Years of experience are not correlated to productivity.<br />Interrupting flow not only causes disruption but frustration.<br />There are two types of work: Individual work is noise sensitive and needs flow.&nbsp;Group work is noise producing. Adapt your workspace to make both kinds of work possible.<br />Measure and try to maximize flow time, but don't let managers access to data.<br />Ignoring the phone must be accepted by corporate policy.<br />Ask people about their workspace conditions, what affects their productivity.<br />Listening to music uses the right part of the braing, which is responsible for creativity.<br />Encourage teams to customize their space.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">People</span><br />People who work for you will be more or less the same at the end as they were at the beginning, so they better be right for the job from the start.<br />Find the right people, make them happy, turn them loose.<br />Success or failure is in the cards from the moment the team is formed and the initial directions set out.<br />Corporate pressure is pushing towards the company average, encouraging you to hire people that look, sound and think like everybody else.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Hiring</span><br />(Tell about hiring a juggler) 'Don't you want to see me juggle?'<br />Make people bring their code portfolio for interviews.<br />Make candidates prepare an audition with the team 10-to-15 minute presentation on some aspect of past work.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Good organizations</span><br />Late promotion is a sign of health.<br />With a low and flat hierarchy, people at the lowest level have, on average more years of experience.<br />Strive to be the best<br />Grow a community feeling.<br />Focus on long term benefits.<br />Widespread sense that you are expected to stay<br />Invest in personal growth<br />Retrain your people<br />When you automate a system, you make it deterministic, so it looses its self-healing ability. A&nbsp;<b>M</b>ethodology (capital 'M' here) can produce the same results on you organization.<br />To achieve convergence of methods, use training, tools and peer review.<br />Don't declare something a standard until it is a de facto standard.<br />Hawtorne effect (experiment of raising and lowering the light) People perform better when they are trying something new.<br />You have to make non-standard approaches to the rule. Whatever standard there is should be brief and gentle.<br />Let a hundred flowers blossom and let a hundred schools of thought contend. (Mao Tse-tung)<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Jelled teams</span><br />Productive teams = challenge + team interaction<br />They have momentum.<br />They have a goal<br />The purpose of a team is not goal attainment but goal achievement.<br />People on jelled teams are often so involved you have to remind them&nbsp;that what they are trying to accomplish is not winning a war.<br />Jelled teams have low turnover and strong sense of identity.<br />Money, status and position for advance matter a lot less. Enjoyment is an obvious sign.<br />You can't make teams jell, just act to improve the odds.<br />Teamicide techniques:<br /><br /><ul><li>Defensive management</li><li>Bureaucracy</li><li>Physical&nbsp;separation</li><li>Fragmentation of people's time</li><li>Quality reduction</li><li>Phony deadlines</li><li>Clique control</li></ul><br />Good managers provide opportunities for the team to succeed together. The best success is the one in which there is no evident management. The best boss is the one who can manage without the team knowing they've been managed.<br /><br />Growing jelled teams:<br /><br /><ul><li>Give people autonomy and responsibility</li><li>Let them work alone, without constant supervision</li><li>They break the rules when they believe in it</li><li>Let them choose mates and projects</li><li>Let them exercise their natural authority in their area of expertise.</li></ul><br />Chemistry for team formation:<br /><br /><ul><li>Make a cult of quality</li><li>Provide satisfying confirmation</li><li>Build a sense of eliteness</li><li>Allow and encourage heterogeneity</li><li>Preserve and protect successful teams.</li><li>Provide strategic but not tactical direction</li></ul><br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Chaos (it is not that bad!)</span><br />Small amounts of disorder are benefitial<br />Pilot projects, war games, brainstorming, provocative training experiences, training, trips, conferences, celebrations, retreats,...<br /><br />If your corporation is fortunate enough to have a self-motivated superachiever on-board, it's enough to say "Define your own job"<br />"Free electrons" have a strong role in choosing their own orbits.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Being a Change Agent</span><br />Focus on one thing to change. Raise people's consciousness of it, so they help you change it.<br />Be careful with motivational posters, they can have the opposite effect.<br />Fuck overtime.<br />Competition inhibits coaching.<br />Any action that rewards team members differently is likely to foster competition.<br />The success of the individual should be tied to the success of the whole.<br />People hate change. Any change.<br />Your enemies are blindly loyals and militantly opposed to change.<br />The fundamental response to change is not logical, but emotional.<br />Celebrate the old as a way to help make change happen.<br />Be aware that chaos is an integral part of change. Otherwise, you mistake it for the new status quo and will want to change back.<br />Change always involves chaos, it is necessary and can't be shortcut. The more painful the chaos, the greater the perceived value of the new status quo.<br />Change won't even get started unless people feel safe when they know they won't be demeaned for proposing or trying a change.<br />Change only has a chance of&nbsp;succeeding&nbsp;if failure is also&nbsp;OK.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Organizational learning</span><br />Learning is limited by an organization's ability to keep its people.<br />If the retrained people leave, investment is lost and learning is gone.<br />Successful&nbsp;learning organizations are always characterized by strong middle management. In order for a vital learning center to form, middle managers must communicate with each other and learn to work together in effective harmony.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Waste</span><br />The ultimate management sin is wasting people's time.<br />Organizations have need of ceremony.<br />Ceremony is good when it fulfills a need for appreciation by the team.<br />Early&nbsp;over-staffing&nbsp;is waste.<br />Fragmented time is waste, it breaks flow.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Community</span><br />Building a community makes a difference, but requires talent, courage and creativity. And an enormous invest of time, to be, at best, the catalyst.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
